<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trve Protestant sovldier fighting valiantly under truths banner, and by the glorious light of Gods word overthrowing the strongest bulwarkes, and subtle stratagems of the Church of Rome. By Hamnet Warde.</title>
            <author>Monginot, François, 1569-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27120</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834082</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834082</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51142)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1836:21, 1345:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trve Protestant sovldier fighting valiantly under truths banner, and by the glorious light of Gods word overthrowing the strongest bulwarkes, and subtle stratagems of the Church of Rome. By Hamnet Warde.</title>
                  <author>Monginot, François, 1569-1637.</author>
                  <author>Ward, Hamnet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.,   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for William Lee at the signe of the Turks-head in fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of François Monginot's "Résolution des doutes, ou, Sommaire decision des controuerses entre l'Eglise reformee &amp; l'Eglise romaine.".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Harvard University Library (reel 1345:13) and the British Library (1836:21).</note>
                  <note>Identified at reel 1345:13 as Wing W768A (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:1"/>
            <p>THE TRVE PROTESTANT SOVLDIER, Fighting valiantly under Truths Banner, <hi>AND</hi> By the glorious light of Gods Word overthrowing the ſtrongeſt Bulwarkes, and ſubtle Stratagems of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By HAMNET WARDE.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of George Miller</figDesc>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>William Lee</hi> at the Signe of the Turks-Head in <hi>Fleet-street.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE AND TRVLY VERTVOVS THE LADY BRIDG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>T BRIANT, all Happineſſe in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He true zeale which you have for the maintenance of the Truth (together with thoſe many favours which your Ladiſhip hath been pleaſed to beſtow on me, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and ſurviving friends) hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me, or rather inforced me to preſent this little Manuall, being the firſt fruits of mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to your Ladiſhips acceptance.</p>
            <p>In that ſhort ſtride of the World, which I have travelled, having found many strong oppoſitions from our adverſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as well at home as beyond Sea) tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Proteſtant Religion, I began ſomewhat to doubt of the truth thereof: But by Gods providence lighting on this ſhort Treatiſe, after the peruſall thereof, I found the Religion
<pb facs="tcp:38564:3"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (if I may ſo call it) ſo ſleightly poasted upon the quickſands of mens frivolous opinions, and contrariwiſe, the Proteſtant Religion ſo ſoundly founded on the true and lively rocke of our ſalvation Chriſt Ieſus, that by Gods grace aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>isting me, neither the bewitching charmes of their devilliſh temptations, nor the fiery darts of their hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perſecutions, ſhall ever be able to divert me from the profeſsion thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherefore having received ſo great comfort thereby my ſelfe, I have laboured with as much as in me lyeth, to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it verbatim out of French into Engliſh, that others alſo may have benefit therby, humbly beſeeching your Ladiſhip to accept thereof, as a token of my ever bounden duty, and your Ladiſhip ſhall thereby encourage me to pray for your long and happy life here on earth, and your eternall happineſſe with God in heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi rend="sup">ps</hi> moſt humble and truly devoted Servant, <hi>Hamnet Warde.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Onſieur Pierre Monginot,</hi> a Gentleman as well learned, as truly noble, forſaking the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and turning to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, his friends being much diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereat, wrote this ſhort Treatiſe, to ſatisfie them, ſhewing them the cauſes which moved him to change his Religion: Which I have tranſlated for thy good out of French into Engliſh; take but as much heed in reading it, as I did labour in the tranſlating it, and God grant thee as much benefit by the Copy, as I had comfort by the Originall.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Hamnet Warde.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:38564:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>CHAPTERS.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>Of the true Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Of the Popes power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Of the worſhipping of Images.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Of Prayer and Service in an unknowne tongue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Of the Invocation of Angels and Saints departed this life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Of Abſtinence from Meats.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Of Abstinence from Marriage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>Of Purgatory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>Of Merits, and Juſtification by Works.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>Of works of Super-erogation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>Of the ſuperaboundant ſatisfactions of Saints and Monkes, which the Pope diſtributes by Indulgences.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. <hi>Of the reall preſence of the Lords body in the Sacrament, and of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. <hi>Of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14. <hi>Of the taking away the cup in the Sacrament.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Decemb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1641.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THO. WYKES</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38564:4"/>
            <head>THE TRVE PROTESTANT SOVLDIER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>Of the true Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Scripture tels us of diverſe kindes of Churches: There is that Church which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Creed, which the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the body of Chriſt, againſt which ſaith our Saviour, Mat. 16. <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile;</hi> which is the Aſſembly of the truly faithfull and elect people of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of part doe already injoy the heavenly pleaſures of Gods kingdome, part now live here on Earth among ſinfull men and infidels, and cannot be diſcerned by the eyes of man: Others not yet borne.</p>
               <p>But beſides this Church of Gods elect, there is another univerſall and viſible Church, which is the Aſſembly of all ſuch as profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38564:5"/>Chriſtians, and to believe in Jeſus Chriſt. This is that Church which Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. cals <hi>the pillar and ground of the truth,</hi> as being bound to defend, and maintaine the truth againſt all thoſe who labour to corrupt or ſuppreſſe it.</p>
               <p>This univerſall viſible Church is compoſed of divers particular Churches; ſuch as were in the Apoſtles time the Church of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> &amp;c. Of theſe particular Churches, ſome are puter than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nay, and there may be ſome ſo corrupted, as that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to be ſaved; namely, as where Idolatry reigneth, and where the benefits of Jeſus Chriſt are abuſed.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is one of theſe particular Churches, wherin reigneth Idolatry. Firſt, in that they call God a Sacrifice made by men. Secondly, becauſe the honour appertaining to God is by them attributed to Saints, in that they ſay the Saints know the hearts of all men, and becauſe they give them and their reliques and Images, a religious worſhip and adoration. Laſtly, becauſe they call the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of Heaven and Earth; for the Soveraigne Royalty of the world is not communicable to the creature.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the benefits of Jeſus Chriſt are therin abus'd; in that they teach that Jeſus Chriſt by his death delivers us from ſinnes committed before Bapiſme, but as for ſinnes committed after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, he hath left us to ſatisfie Gods juſtice for them, by ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory pains, as well here as in Purgatory. Thus then let it be; that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be a particular viſible Church, and it more corrupt than any other, although ſhe terme her ſelfe, the univerſall Church, as if there were no other Church beſides; whereas indeed the Churches of <hi>Syria, Greece, Armenia,</hi> and <hi>Affrica</hi> be more pure and mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>cient then the Roman, and no way ſubject therunto. All th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>h the holy Scripture, and the Creed attribute to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church of Gods elect, or the univerſall viſible Church, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by an intolerable abuſe and uſurpation attributes unto her ſelf; as if in the holy Scripture, there were no other Church ſpoken off, but the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> or as if ſhee alone were <hi>the pillar and ground of the truth.</hi> And when Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. ſends two Brothers being at ſtrife to the judgement of the Church, ſaying, <hi>Tell it the Church, and if he neglect to heare the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen man and a Publican;</hi> theſe Gentlemen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38564:5"/>would needs make us beleeve that he ſends ſuch as doubt in matters of Faith and Doctrin to the judgment of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they call univerſall; but reade the paſſage and you ſhall ſee that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſpeaks not there of doubts touching Religion, but of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and broyles which happen betweene man and man, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he ſpeaks not of the Church univerſall, but of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſome particular Church; for to appeaſe a quarrell between two Neighbours, men doe not betake themſelves to the univerſall Church.</p>
               <p>In this then there appeares a very great abuſe, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> being indeed but a particular Church ſtiles her ſelfe the univerſall Church, and in that ſhe being full of errours, vaunts her ſelfe nevertheleſſe to be without any errour; nay more, that it is impoſſible for her to erre, and leaſt her errours ſhould be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the glorious light of Gods holy Word, the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, ſhe doth not only hinder the people from reading the word, and reade it in the Church in a language which the people underſtandeth not, but endeavours alſo to take away all its force and authority, for they make the people beleeve that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſoveraigne Judge in all matters of difference in Religion, by this meanes he that will accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of any errour may be ſure to looſe his proceſſe, ſeeing ſhe alone is ſoveraigne Judge in her owne cauſe. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth likewiſe affirme that it is impoſſible for her to erre in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of the holy Scripture, and that it is in her power to make conſtructions of the like authority with the word of God; which is indeed no leſſe then to place her ſelfe in Gods ſeat. For as there is none but the King that can give an interpretation to his edict, that may be of equall force with the edict it ſelfe: So there is none but God alone that may give ſuch a conſtruction unto the Word of God, as may be of the like power and authority with the Word of God. And there is nothing more certaine then that ſuch an interpreter is greater then the Law-giver, ſithence he giveth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Law ſuch a ſenſe as he pleaſeth, and the people taught to rely more on that, then on the Law it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And to be ſure that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be not any way ſubject unto the holy Scripture, they maintaine that it is the Church that doth authorize the Scripture, and which gives it all its power and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38564:6"/>authority, as if the Subject could give authority unto Lawes, or as if the Word of God did receive its authority from men.</p>
               <p>To this end the Doctours of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſay, that the Church is more ancient then the holy Scripture; but doth it therefore follow that the Church muſt be above the Scripture: the people are they not many of them older then the King, yet are they nevertheleſſe ſubject both to the King and to his Lawes, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there be many Doctrines in the holy Scripture more ancient then the Church.</p>
               <p>But ſay they we ſhould not know that it were the Scripture, if the Church did not tell us ſo; but doth it follow thence I pray you that the Church muſt be above the Scripture? If I ſhould ſay I doe not know which is the King, and if my friend ſhould ſhew me, doth it therefore follow that my friend muſt be above the King? Many ſerve for witneſſes unto perſons unto whom they are farre inferiour.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe to undervalue the authority of the Scripture, and to ſtrengthen that of the Church, they ſay, that the holy Scripture is a dead thing and cannot ſpeake, and conſequently may not be Judge, for ſay they a Judge muſt be able to ſpeake, as the Church is. This is moſt falſe and deceitfull, for the holy Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth enough, and if it ſpeaks not, enough it is that it guides us. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> forſooth will be the rule it ſelfe, and not ſubject to any Law, but will be Judge both of the Law, and of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Thus are men become Gods Judges, and guilty perſons ſhall be infallible and ſoveraigne Judges of the ſence and authority of the Law, which concernes their owne crime; by this meanes they need not feare to be condemned, but will they, nill they at the day of Judgement, they ſhall be judged by this very word, over which they now thus uſurpe authority, then ſhall that pratling Judge be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to keep ſilence.</p>
               <p>So then theſe Gentlemen in ſending the people to the Church for the deciding of doubts in faith, diſtract their minds with an innumerable company of doubts and difficulties, for how ſhall an ignorant man know that there muſt be a Church in the world? If they ſay he may know it by the Scripture, it is then neceſſary that he be acquainted with the Scripture; and thus the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38564:6"/>of the Church ſhould be founded on the Scripture; and when the Church teacheth this or that, how ſhall the people know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be conformable to the Word of God, ſithence the reading of Gods Word is abſolutely forbidden them, and there being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches diſagreeing one with the other, how can the poore people diſcerne that which teacheth lyes, from that which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the truth; ſeeing the very rule of truth, which is the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a book utterly forbidden them?</p>
               <p>Shall they follow the multitude? Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>That the gate is wide which leadeth to perdition,</hi> and there are ten times as many <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> as there are Chriſtians, ſhall they believe miracles? our Saviour faith <hi>Marke</hi> 13. <hi>There ſhall come falſe teachers, working miracles whereby to ſeduce, if it were poſſible the very elect:</hi> ſhall they have regard to ſeats and ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? The Churches of <hi>Greece</hi> have alſo had their ſeats ſince the Apoſtles, and the Churches of <hi>Syria</hi> theirs, and brag of S. <hi>Peters</hi> chair; and yet all theſe are quite contrary to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and indeed more ancient. Jeſus Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles having preached there, and beeing the firſt Inſtitutours of them.</p>
               <p>We doe not here diſpute of S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſuperiority over the reſt of the Apoſtles; he might be the firſt in order, authority or virtue, and yet not have any ſuperiority of juriſdiction. But that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; the queſtion is, whether the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> be S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, as the head of the univerſall Church? which is the principall point of the Papiſts Religion, wherof nevertheleſſe there is not one word ſpoken in all the Scripture. The Biſhops of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> were Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Succeſſours, not as Apoſtles but as particular Biſhops of thoſe cities: So the queſtion is not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the afore-ſaid Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> be Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſour in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Rome,</hi> but whether he ſucceeds him in the Apoſtleſhip, as the head of the whole Church. This is that which we ſlatly deny, and which they can never proove; or if they could ſo prove it, yet the Pope having corrupted Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Biſhoprick into an abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lute temporall Monarchy, had long ſince that loſt his ſucceſſion.</p>
               <p>To conclude there being but one holy Scripture, and there being many contrary Churches, and the Doctors of theſe Churches being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38564:7"/>apt to ſeeke their owne profit, and ſubject to be carried away with diverſe evill affections, but the holy Scripture being an incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judge; let us have recourſe to this holy Word of God, in the which if there be any obſcurity, there is notwithſtanding e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough left, which needs no interpretation, which is ſufficient to make us wiſe unto Salvation, as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II. <hi>Of the Popes power.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> calleth himſelfe Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſour, not only as being Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but as being alſo the Head of the univerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Church. Which power he extends ſo farre as to give and take away Kingdomes, to diſtribute of crownes, to diſpence with Chriſtians from keeping their oathes and vowes, to canonize Saints, to give Lawes to the univerſall Church, to forgive ſins, to take ſoules out of Purgatory, to judge ſoveraignly and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole of all points and differences in Religion, vaunting that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to erre in faith, and for theſe conſiderations quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying himſelfe god on Earth, the Spouſe of the Church, and a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, cauſing Kings to kiſſe his feet, and making himſelf a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip, terming himſelf Gods Vicar.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe I have read very carefully Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Epiſtles, and have compared them with the Popes Buls, wherby he thunders down Kings, and degrades them, publiſheth grand pardons; but I can finde no concordance at all, the one with the other; for Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in his Epiſtles ſpeaks not any wiſe of his Superiority, not of his power, neither is there one word ſpoken of his Soveraignty, or as being head of the Church, which is a very ſtrange thing, that a Soveraigne ſhould write unto his ſubjects, without mentioning one word that might intimate his Soveraignty.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38564:7"/>
               <p>I finde alſo that the Apoſtles did conteſt among themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the priority; and that Jeſus Chriſt did decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, not telling them that he had made Saint <hi>Peter</hi> chiefe over the reſt, but forbidding them all, not ſo much as to ſpeake of the priority any more, Luk. 22. <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>exerciſe Lordſhip over them, but it ſhall not be ſo with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> having confeſſed our Saviour to be the Chriſt, the ſon of the living God, our Saviours anſwer to him is not, <hi>Tu es Petrus, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per te Petrum, adificabo eccleſiam meam,</hi> but <hi>tu es Petrus, &amp; ſuper hanc petram, &amp;c.</hi> which rock is Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, as it is ſaid 1 Cor. 10. <hi>That rocke was Chriſt,</hi> and in the ſecond chapter to the <hi>Eph.</hi> he is called the <hi>corner ſtone,</hi> and S. <hi>Peter</hi> 1. <hi>cp.</hi> 2. cals him, <hi>a living Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon why our Saviour ſpake to S. <hi>Peter</hi> alone, was becauſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> had there alone confeſſed him to be the Chriſt; but the ſame power that he gave to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> to binde and to looſe, and to remit ſins, he gives elſwhere alſo to the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 18. &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 20. 23. Likewiſe in the ſecond chapter to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> all the Apoſtles are ſet for the foundation of the Church, <hi>being built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and of the Prophets.</hi> See alſo <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.14.</p>
               <p>And certainly if the Apoſtles had underſtood that Ieſus Chriſt had given S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Superiority, never would they again after that have conteſted betweene themſelves for the preheminence, as they do in <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. one day before the death of the Lord.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo in <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. ſaith, that he <hi>withſtood</hi> St. Peter <hi>to the face</hi>; which ſheweth ſufficiently that he was nothing ſubject to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the ſame Chapter a little before, he ſaith, That <hi>the Gospell of uncircumciſion was committed to him, as the Goſpell of circumciſion was unto</hi> Peter: here we ſee them fellow-labourers together, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was to preach to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that ſame chapter alſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets the Apoſtle S. <hi>James</hi> before S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying <hi>James, Cephas and John, who ſeemed to be pillars.</hi> So alſo S. <hi>John</hi> in the firſt chapter of his Goſpell ſets <hi>Andrew</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Peter,</hi> where he ſaith, Philip <hi>was of Bethſaida the city of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew <hi>and</hi> Peter, and in the 1 Cor. 9. <hi>The Brothers of the Lord and</hi> Cephas, and in the 8. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the Apoſtles ſend <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to preach in <hi>Samaria.</hi> Oh what a brave thing it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38564:8"/>were now a dayes to ſee many Biſhops aſſemble together, and ſend the Pope to preach in <hi>England</hi> or elſwhere? They object that our Saviour ſaid to St. <hi>Peter</hi> three times, <hi>Feed my ſheepe;</hi> true, but they cannot inferre from thence that he made him the head of the univerſall Church; for our Saviour ſaid not to S. <hi>Peter</hi> feed thou my ſheep alone, or as a Soveraigne; and indeed the ſame commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is given to all the Miniſters of Gods Word in the 20. of the <hi>Acts, Take heed therefore,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul unto your ſelves, and to all the flocke, over the which the Lord hath made you over-ſeers, to feede the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloud,</hi> and in the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>Feede the flocke of Chriſt which is among you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt then ſpeaks to S. <hi>Peter</hi> alone, becauſe that a little before he had denied him, and he only had need to be reſtabliſhed in his commiſſion, that had failed in it. Another reaſon why our Saviour repeats the words thrice is, becauſe that he had denied him thrice; he draws from him three confeſſions to remedy his treble denyall, which done, he did againe eſtabliſh him in the charge of a Shepheard of his flocke, from the which he might plainly perceive that he had fallen.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe I will not deny but that S. <hi>Peter</hi> might be the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among the Apoſtles in age, zeale, cloquance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but by no meanes in ſuperiority of juriſdiction, wherby to have power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them.</p>
               <p>However put the caſe that S. <hi>Peter</hi> had beene the chiefe of the Apoſtles and their Superiour, what doth that make for the Pope of <hi>Rome?</hi> They ſay S. <hi>Peter</hi> died at <hi>Rome,</hi> which is indeed very doubtfull: nevertheleſſe put the caſe he did dye there; for I may ſay then that the Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ought to be the head of the Church: for our Saviour Chriſt farre greater than St. <hi>Peter</hi> dyed at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Where is the leaſt mention in all Gods Word that S. <hi>Peter</hi> did leave one to ſucceed him in the charge of his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and as the head of the Church? And when S. <hi>Peter</hi> was dead in all reaſon and conſcience, if any ſhould ſucceed him, ought it not to be the Apoſtle S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that excellent Apoſtle, which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus loved, rather then <hi>Linus</hi> S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſciple.</p>
               <p>Moreover by all the Hiſtories of the lives of the Popes, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that the people of <hi>Rome</hi> did chooſe their Biſhop, who ſeeth not hereby, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was not the head of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38564:8"/>the univerſall Church, for who gave the people of <hi>Rome</hi> power to give a head to the Church of the whole world? and to ſet up <hi>Linus</hi> above the Apoſtles? In an elective Kingdom, when a King is to be choſen, every quarter of the Kingdome, and every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty ſends it's Deputies to make the election; the voyces of one city cannot conclude of any thing wherin the whole Kingdome hath intereſt.</p>
               <p>Nay I ſay more, though S. <hi>Peter</hi> had been the head of the Church, and though he had reſided at <hi>Rome,</hi> and had left his charge to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (which are all ſuch preſuppoſitions, as they ſhall never be able to proove) yet hath the Pope long ſince fallen from his charge, and conſequently loſt his honour; by comporting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe quite contrary to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to a ſpirituall Paſtour, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a temporall Monarch, having amaſſed unto himſelf ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of riches, that the Superiours and Kings of the Earth are poore in compariſon. As for his Doctrine, the Chapters fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhall be imployed, to ſhew, that it is abſolutely contrary to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Again, S. <hi>Peter</hi> never made himſelf a religious worſhip, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. v. 25. he hinders <hi>Cornelius</hi> from worſhipping him, ſaying, <hi>Stand up, I my ſelfe alſo am a man.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſet himſelf above God, as doth the Pope, glorying that he can diſpence with men from keeping their vowes made unto God: He that can diſpence with a ſervant from obeying his maſter, muſt be greater then the maſter: The Pope diſpenceth with men from obeying Gods commands, doth he not then make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe greater then God? He diſpenceth alſo with Subjects from keeping their oath of allegiance which they have ſworne to their Soveraigne, inciting therby to rebellion. He permits a man to marry his Neece, and his wives ſiſter, things abſclutely againſt Gods expreſſe command in the 18. &amp; 20. Chapters of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Faults committed againſt the Pope are many of them accounted ſo hideous, that they are not to be pardoned under a great ſumme of mony, or it may be, two or three years pilgrimage; but as for ſins which tend only to Gods diſhonour, as ſwearing, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Sabbath-breaking, and ſo though they be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atly forbidden in Gods holy Word, yet if they doe not any way intrench upon the Popes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38564:9"/>prerogative, not derogate from his ſuprem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cy, theſeare eſteem'd but petty faults, half a dozen <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er noſters,</hi> and two or three <hi>ave Maries</hi> are a ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ficient ſatisfaction for a thouſand ſuch ſins.</p>
               <p>Briefly he boaſts himſelf to be above the Church, and ſaith that the Church is above the Word of God; by this reckoning then the Pope is two degrees above Gods Word.</p>
               <p>Moreover in the Councels where the Pope is preſent, the holy Scripture is ſet at his feet; as it was in the laſt Councell of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran:</hi> I leave any reaſonable man to judge, whether by this it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth not plainly, that he tramples under his feet the Word of God?</p>
               <p>To conclude, when I reade in the ſecond Epiſtle of the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians, That there ſhall come a man, which is called the man of ſinne, and the ſonne of perdition, that ſhall call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe God and exalt himſelfe above God; boaſting himſelfe in ſignes and miracles:</hi> And in the 17. of the <hi>Revelation, of the great Whore that is cloathed in ſcarlet, that ſeduceth Kings, and maketh them drunke with the bloud of her fornication, that hath her habitation in the City ſeated on ſeven mountains</hi> (that is to ſay, the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>) I have ſearched every where, but can find none to whom this may be ſo truly applyed, as to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the worſhipping of Images.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe third abuſe which I have taken notice of in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the ſervice which they doe unto Saints departed this life: The Councels of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> namely, the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> command that Images be adored.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Paris</hi> a little before Lent you may ſee the people goe in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Image of our Lady, to have permiſſion to eat butter. The women come and rub their Chappelets on the feet of the I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they light them torches at mid-day, they kiſſe them, they make courſies to them, they bring them preſents, and carry them all about in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38564:9"/>proceſſion with great ſolemnity. Nay more then that, you may ſee many Images of Saints that never were: As of the three Kings, Saint <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Saint <hi>Margaret,</hi> Saint <hi>Martiall,</hi> Saint <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſuline,</hi> Saint <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> Saint <hi>Catherine,</hi> and many other ſuch like fantaſticall Saints that never were in the world.</p>
               <p>Many prayers likewiſe there are which they mumble out before ſuch their dumbe petty-gods, as that unto the croſſe, <hi>Ave Lignum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphale,</hi> &amp;c. and diverſe others, which prayers if they intend them to Gods honour, they muſt alſo cauſe thoſe things to which they ſpeake, to underſtand what they ſay unto them: No man except he be fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke will ſpeake to the Kings Image with a conceit that thereby he doth the King any honour.</p>
               <p>All theſe inventions ſerve on purpoſe to lull the people aſleep in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, wherefore they call Images the books of the ignorant, they themſelves alſo hide them in time of Lent, which is the time of their devotion, that they may not hinder their devotion.</p>
               <p>That which cauſeth all this miſery is, that they take away from the common people the holy Scripture, for having forbidden them Gods Word, it was moſt neceſſary for them to finde them out ſomewhat or other to muſe on; for this end they take out of the table of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements which they deliver unto the people, the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, wherein God forbids the worſhipping of Images, and <hi>the making of the likeneſſe of any thing in heaven or in earth, Deut.</hi> 5.8. Thus they doe in ſome places clip and crop the word of God, and in other ſome patch it and peece it, wherby to make it anſwerable to their owne inventions.</p>
               <p>As I cannot therefore but pitty the miſerable eſtate of thoſe people who are thus kept in darkneſſe and ignorance: ſo I cannot but moſt juſtly condemne the intollerable uſurpation of their Leaders, who to ſerve their owne unſatiable avarice, hating the glorious light of Gods word, endeavour by all meanes to eclipſe the ſame; and thereby bring themſelves, and all ſuch as are carried away with their lives and doctrine (without Gods great mercy) to everlaſting deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38564:10"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IIII. <hi>Of Prayer and ſerving God in an unknowne tongue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe of the moſt deadly and moſt dangerous abuſes of the Church of Rome in my judgement is, their praying to God in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage that oft times the perſon that prayeth underſtandeth not; for S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 1. to the <hi>Corinthians, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 15. willeth us to <hi>pray with understanding.</hi> How can we expect that God ſhould grant our requeſts, if we our ſelves doe not know what we would have. True indeed, God underſtandeth all languages, but in prayer God hath not ſo much regard to the tongue, but to the heart, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be then well diſpoſed, when it knowes not what the tongue doth ſay: For the tongue is given unto men to teſtifie the thoughts of their hearts, ſo that he who prayeth, not knowing what he ſaith, doth not expreſſe his thoughts by his words; by this meanes he doth as it were act a Comedy before God: There is no Prince that will ſuffer a man to prate thus to him, although he underſtandeth all languages. And indeed we can hardly reprove a man more ſharply, then by telling him, friend, thou knoweſt not what thou ſayeſt. Thus then they both mocke God, and loſe their labour. The abuſe is yet farre greater in the reading of the Epiſtle and Goſpell to the people in the Church in Latine, whereof moſt of them underſtand not ſo much as one word. How can they then yeeld obedience unto ſuch doctrines as they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not? Is not this the curſe which God Almighty denounceth by his Prophets, <hi>I will henceforth ſpeake to this people in another tongue, and with other lips, and ſo they will not underſtand me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.11. And the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that in the Church he hadrather ſpeake five words with underſtanding, that thereby he might teach others alſo, then a thouſand words in an unknowne tongue,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. And in the ſame Chapter a little before he ſaith, <hi>Except ye utter by the tongue words eaſie to be underſtood, how ſhall it be knowne what is ſpoken? for ye ſhall ſpeake unto the ayre, therefore if I know not the meaning of the voyce, I ſhall be to him that ſpeaketh a Barbarian, and he that ſpeaketh ſhall be a Barbarian unto me,</hi> See then an admirable Religion; for they ſpeake to ſtocks and ſtones which underſtand no language;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38564:10"/>and to the people, leaſt they ſhould underſtand what they ſay, they ſpeake altogether in Latine. The people indeed gee to ſee the Maſſe, but they cannot underſtand a word of it, nay and very often the Prieſts themſelves have much adoe to underſtand it. But ſay they we reade the Maſſe in Latine, that ſtrangers alſo may have benefit thereby. A pretty hypocriticall excuſe it is indeed; for ſuppoſe there be ten, twenty, or more ſtrangers in a Church, is it fit that they ſhould have ſervice read in a language which they know, and all the reſt of the people ſit like fooles, and underſtand never a word: Beſides, if they did meane as they pretend, ſurely in ſuch a City as <hi>Paris</hi> they would have in a Church for ſtrangers to reſort unto, the ſervice read in Latine, and in all the reſt, in their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey language, which they all underſtand.</p>
               <p>They alſo abſolutely forbid any man to reade the holy Scripture, without a ſpeciall Licence from the Pope, or his Factor; and to tranſlate it into the vulgar tongue, which is as much to ſay, as that they will not ſuffer a childe to read his Fathers will; and that God Almighty is become ſuſpected as if he had given us his word to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſent Epiſtles to the <hi>Epheſians, Corinthians, Philippians,</hi> &amp;c. He writ unto every of them in their owne tongue, to the end that all might reade and know what he writ unto them. And I pray why may not we now reade thoſe ſame Epiſtles in our owne language, as well as they read them in theirs?</p>
               <p>Whereupon alſo the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>I charge you by the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Epiſtle be read unto all the holy brethren.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Acts</hi> 17. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. the <hi>Bereans</hi> are commended, <hi>for that they ſearched the Seriptures daily whether thoſe things were ſo,</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preached unto them.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 2 of <hi>Timothy, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>prayſeth his Diſciple</hi> Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, <hi>becauſe that from a childe he had knowne the holy Scriptures.</hi> In a word, this is a new ſtartup invention, and ſuch a knavery as is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome heard of, to forbid the people to reade the word of God, leſt they ſhould become heretickes, whereas indeed it is only to maske them with ignorance, for feare leſt by the light of Gods Word, their Religion ſhould plainly appeare to be, as it is indeed, full of groſſe errours and hypocriſie.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38564:11"/>
               <p>In thoſe countries where the Inquiſition is, bawdy-houſes are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, and the Pope doth gather out of them great ſummes of money for tribute: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooliſh pamphlets, and immodeſt Love-bookes are printed <hi>cum privilegio;</hi> but if they finde but one Bible, either Italian, Spaniſh, or the like, 'tis accounted a crime which deſerveth no leſſe then death, and a caſe worthy of the Inquiſition. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had it not been for the reformed Church, that is to ſay, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from Popery, the Bible had long ſince been buried in oblivion, and no mention made thereof: For as theeves hate the light, leſt their evill deeds ſhould be diſcovered: ſo doe thoſe Doctors of the Church of Rome labour to obſcure the light of Gods Word, leſt their hypocriticall inventions, and new found devilli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h plots, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſerve their owne unſatiable luſts, ſhould bee brought to light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V. <hi>Of the Invocation of Angels and Saints departed this Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Invocation of Angels and Saints deceaſed, hath indeed a ſhew of devotion and humility, but it is never the leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to to the word of God, which flatly forbids us to give any divine ſervice or worſhip unto Angels; as in the ſecond Chapter of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians, Let no man beguile you of your reward, in a voluntary humility, and worſhipping of Angels, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding into thoſe things which he hath not ſeen.</hi> We beleeve in God alone, and the ſame Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the tenth Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes</hi> forbiddeth us to worſhip any other then him in whom we beleeve; how ſaith he, <hi>ſhall they call on him on whom they have not beleeved?</hi> And our Creed teacheth us to beleeve in the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy-Ghoſt, but not in any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatſoever. So likewiſe in the two and twentieth of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38564:11"/>when Saint <hi>John</hi> fell downe to worſhip before the feet of the Angell, <hi>the Angell forbad him, ſaying, ſee thou doe it not, for I am thy fellow-ſervant, worſhip God.</hi> Saint <hi>James</hi> in the firſt of <hi>James, ver.</hi> 6. <hi>Willeth us to pray in faith;</hi> and the Apoſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> 14. Chapter, tels us, that <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Invocation of Saints cannot be done in faith, becauſe it is not grounded on the word of God; for the ſame Apoſtle in the tenth of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſaith, <hi>that ſaith commeth by hearing, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by the word of God;</hi> and none of the Doctors of the Church of Rome could ever produce any argument out of the word of God, whereby to prove that religious worſhip which they give unto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or Saints deceaſed, either lawfull or neceſſary. Againe, if it be neceſſary for us to pray to Saints, it muſt likewiſe moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow that they muſt know our hearts and thoughts; for how ſhould they elſe diſcerne hypocrites from ſuch as pray in ſincerity. Which is quite contrary to Gods word in the ſecond booke of the <hi>Chronicles, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>thou onely</hi> (ſaith the wiſe King <hi>Solomon) knoweſt the hearts of the children of men.</hi> Likewiſe, to ſay that the Saints ſee all things in the face of God as in a glaſſe, were to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye, having no warrant from the word of God for the truth thereof: And were it ſo that the Saints knew all things, then were they equall with God Almighty in wiſedome and knowledge. But the Scripture ſaith that the Saints know not the day of judgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. and <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. And the wiſe man in the ninth <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> excludeth the dead from any knowledge of earthly things; <hi>The dead</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>know not any thing, neither have they any more a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any thing that is done under the Sunne.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> Chapter 14. ſpeaking of a diſeaſed father, <hi>his children</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>come to honour, and he knoweth it not, and they are brought low, but he perceiveth it not of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their ordinary excuſe is, that they goe to God by Saints, as men goe to the King by his officers: But the caſe is not alike: For a King cannot be every where, neither doth he know all things, and it is not poſſible that every one ſhould have acceſſe to him: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be hath need to be informed of the truth of things by perſons put in truſt therefore. It is not thus with God, for he knoweth all things, and doth ſee and behold all the creatures in the world at once, and knoweth and underſtandeth all mens prayers, not needing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38564:12"/>either Saints or Angels to informe him thereof. And although this compariſon were allowable, yet if a King cals any one unto him, certainly he will not be well pleaſed if that perſon ſhould goe to any of his officers before he come to him. Thus God invites us, ſaying, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary, and heavy laden, and I will refreſh you, Mat.</hi> 11. He doth not bid us goe to Saint <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſelin,</hi> Saint <hi>Margarite,</hi> or any other ſuch like ſolicitors; Nay more, God cals us his children, and therefore if we ſhould not goe unto him in all our neceſſities when he cals us, we ſhould ſhew our ſelves very undutifull, and unworthy of ſo high a calling.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>we have one only Advocate with the Father, namely, the Sonne of God, our Lord Jeſus,</hi> and there is none other. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 1 <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 2. ſaith thus, <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator, between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> As therefore there is but one God, ſo there is but one Mediator. And Saint <hi>John</hi> in his 1. Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>We have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Christ the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins.</hi> And in the 14. Chapter of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpell, <hi>I</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>am the way, the truth and the life, no man commeth unto the Father but by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their greateſt abuſe is yet behind; which is, that they doe not onely make the Saints our Mediators, but alſo our Redeemers: For in the Maſſe the Prieſts pray for ſalvation through their merits: For they ſay that the Saints undergoe more puniſhment and paines then their ſiunes deſerve. Hence they gather their ſuperabundant ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, which the Pope hoordeth up in the treaſury of the Church, and diſtributes them by Indulgences, ſo that any one that hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney may goe to the Pope, and purchaſe as many merits as will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie Gods juſtice for all the ſins that he commits all his life long, let him ſinne as much as he can. This alſo is a tricke which ſerves very well for the Popes profit, and to exalt his dignity; and is founded on the unwritten word, that is to ſay, on their owne helliſh Inventions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38564:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of faſting and abstinence from certainements.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe grand enemy of our ſalvation hath laboured with might and maine for the accompliſhment of the prophecye of the Apoſtle. S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> where he ſpeaketh thus; <hi>Now the Spirit spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing spirits, and doctrines of devils, forbidding to marry, and commanding to abſtaine from meats, which God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be received with thanksgiving of them which beleeve and know the truth, for every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed, if it be received with thanks giving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This prophecye of the Apoſtle is long agoe accompliſhed in the Doctors of the Church of Rome: For doe not they both forbid marriage, and command to abſtaine from meats? which abſtinence is alſo flatly condemned by the ſame Apoſtle in the tenth Chapter of the 1. to the <hi>Corinthians, Whatſoever</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is ſold in the ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that eat, asking no question for conſcience ſake; for the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof: If any of them that beleeve not bid you to a feaſt, and ye be diſpoſed to goe, whatſoever is ſet before you that eat, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake.</hi> And in the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians, he condemneth thoſe who ſay, touch not, taſte not, handle not.</hi> And to the end that we might not thinke that he ſpeaks only of thoſe who abſtaine from meats which they conceive filthy in their owne nature, he declareth plainly, that he ſpeaketh of ſuch <hi>as abſlaine themſelves in humility, and in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary devotion, puniſhing their owne bodies, not sparing their fleſh; which doctrines</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have indeed a ſhew of wiſedome, in will worſhip and humility, and neglecting of the body, not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of Rome is full of theſe obſervations, there being above five moneths in the yeare wherein ſome abſtaine from ſome kind of meat or other. Obſervations, which we cannot find that they were ever practiſed by our Saviour, or his Apoſtles. Theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinences
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38564:13"/>they give unto God in part of payment, and their faſtings they account for ſatisfactions; as if a man ſhould thinke to pay his debts by faſting, preſuming that his Creditors will abate him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, becauſe that ſuch a day he did eat nothing but fiſh for his dinner.</p>
               <p>Nay the abuſe is now come ſo farre, as that one man may faſt for another, and ſo ſatisfie for him; and that a man to whom the Prieſt hath ſet certaine faſts for pennance, may for a peece of money buy them out.</p>
               <p>Sobriety and abſtinence of themſelves are indeed good and holy duties, ſo as they be not abuſed by ſuperſtition, and by thinking to merit any thing unto our ſelves thereby; for ſo that which is in it ſelfe an exerciſe of humility, is changed into an efficient cauſe of pride; and that which ſhould ſerve to lay open our ſinnes before God, is made a covert for our hypocrifie.</p>
               <p>This is alſo another device, whereby the Pope increaſeth his dignity, and gathers vaſt ſummes of money to his treaſury.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of abſtinence from Marriage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for forbidding to marry, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us, that <hi>it is the doctrine of devils.</hi> In the Apoſtles time marriage was permitted unto the Miniſters of the Church, witneſſe the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 3. <hi>A Biſhop</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>must be blameleſſe, the husband of one wife, ruling well his owne houſe, having his children in ſubiection with all gravity;</hi> and a little after, <hi>Let the Deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children and their owne houſes well.</hi> So likewiſe in the 11. verſe commandeth <hi>that their wives be grave, not ſtande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſober, faithfull in all things;</hi> and in the ſeventh Chapter of the 1 to the <hi>Corinthians, to avoid fornication, let every man have his owne wife, and let every woman have her owne husband.</hi> Note here the word <hi>every,</hi> to the end that neither Prieſts nor any other may be excepted. Likewiſe <hi>to avoid fornication,</hi> this commandement is made unto all ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38564:13"/>as are ſubject to fall into fornication, ſo that Prieſts are no way exempted from it, for they alſo being but fleſh and bloud, are ſubject to the like infirmities as others are.</p>
               <p>We reade alſo that the Prophets and chiefe ſacrificers were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. Likewiſe we reade that the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was married, for in the 1. Chapter of Saint <hi>Marke</hi> there is mention made of <hi>Peters wives mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in the Church of Rome Marriage is forbidden Clarkes and Prieſts: If a Prieſt doth wantonly dally with a wench in the open ſtreets, no man regards that; for at Rome the Prelates goe publikely into the bawdy houſes; but to ſee a Prieſt or Capuchin, or ſuch like married, it were a thing very prodigious.</p>
               <p>They object that the Prieſts have made a ſolemne vow to abſtaine from Marriage; but have they not alſo made a vow to keep Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, that forbid fornication, and that commandeth us to <hi>marry rather then to burne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vowes indeed are good, when they promiſe good things, and ſuch as are in our power to performe; but it is not alwayes in mans power to abſtaine from fornication. A ſingle life is without queſtion very good and commendable, but in thoſe only which have the gift of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency; the which, either none at all, or very few have attained unto.</p>
               <p>Moreover, where is the leaſt Commandement in all Gods Word, whereby honeſt Marriage is forbidden, either to thoſe of the Clergy or others? No, no, this certainly was invented for the better main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Popes dignity; for the Pope having been at great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in erecting of bawdy-houſes in <hi>Rome,</hi> and elſewhere, it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for him to find out ſome deviſe to get reſort thereunto, by the forbidding thoſe of the Clergy to marry, who now are far better cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers then any other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Purgatory.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Purgatory of the Church of Rome hath this maxime for its foundation, That by the paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38564:14"/>are diſcharged, and delivered from the guilt and puniſhment of our ſinnes committed before Baptiſme; but as for ſinnes committed after Baptiſme, it is left to us to ſatisfie Gods juſtice, in this life by ſuch penances as the Church ſhall thinke fit to enjoyne us; and afterwards in afire which they call Purgatory; which torment is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated and ſhortened by the prayers and offerings of the Living, and by the Popes Indulgences.</p>
               <p>Surely the proofe of this doctrine they have out of their unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word, for there is not ſo much as mention made of any ſuch matter in Gods Word: However hereby they have amaſſed infinite riches unto the Popes Treaſury; becauſe theſe Maſſes, and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, by the which they ſay this torment is mitigated, and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened are ſold at a very high rate; for they never ſay any Maſſe for any perſon deceaſed, except he or his friends doe give ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to the maintenance of the Church: No, no, ſuch ſpeciall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as theſe are not for ſuch poore people as are not able to purchaſe them.</p>
               <p>Concerning this Purgatory, we reade nothing, neither in the old, nor new Teſtament; but on the contrary we reade of divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who by death have immediately entred into Paradiſe, and there reſted in peace. Witneſſe the <hi>good old Simeon,</hi> in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of Saint <hi>Luke, who had a promiſe after having ſeen the Meſſias to depart in peace.</hi> Likewiſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of <hi>Timothy</hi> 4. witneſſeth, <hi>that after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fought a good fight, he was to receive a crowne of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſoule of poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the 16. <hi>Luke</hi> is carried immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after its departure out of the body into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, where it is comforted, whileſt wicked <hi>Dives</hi> is grievouſly tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in hell-fire. Our Saviour ſaid to the penitent theefe that was crucified with him, <hi>this day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt then that he went not into Purgatory.</p>
               <p>The Angell of God in the 14. Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may rest from their labours, and their works doe follow them.</hi> Doe they reſt from their labours? how are they then tormented in a terrible blaſting fire? Againe the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. ſaith, <hi>That if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle be diſſolved, we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternall in the heavens.</hi> Now I doe much admire how the Apoſtle
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38564:14"/>ſhould be ſo far overſeen, as to forget Purgatory, which they imagine to be between theſe two.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we reade in the firſt Chapter of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>that the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſinne;</hi> and in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Chapter to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> we reade, <hi>that God hath forgiven us all our treſpaſſes.</hi> How is it then that theſe blaſphemers dare to accuſe God of ſo high an injuſtice, as to exact the payment of thoſe debts, which are already paid? and to ſcorch his poore chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in a hot burning fire, for the puniſhment of thoſe ſins, which he hath already freely forgiven us in Jeſus Chriſt? Thus to deale with our very enemies were inhumanity; how then can we imagine that the God of heaven, who is goodneſſe it ſelfe, ſhould doe thus with his ſervants?</p>
               <p>I confeſſe that God, after having pardoned our ſinnes, ceaſeth not to chaſtiſe us in this life, to amend us, and to keep us alwayes in awe of his Majeſty. Theſe puniſhments are none other then fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly chaſtiſements and corrections. If God did not thus correct us, he would puniſh us more in not correcting us; for the ſinner that is not thus recalled from his evill wayes, ſnorts in his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and luls himſelfe aſleep in his ſinnes; but I ſhall never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that the moſt juſt, and onely wiſe God, after having freely forgiven us all our ſinnes in Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould afterwards take pleaſure to torment us thouſands of yeares in a terrible hot burning fire. Beſides, if there be a Furgatory, why may not the death and paſſion of our Saviour Chriſt Jeſus be ſufficient to deliver ſoules from thence, as well as the Popes Indulgences? and if the Pope can draw ſoules out of Purgatory at his pleaſure, I muſt needs judge him a very uncharitable perſon to let ſo many thouſands lye there, in ſuch grievous torments, for want of money to buy Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe paſſages which they alleadge out of the Scripture, to prove this their imaginary Purgatory, they are all ſpoken alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorically, and figuratively: As that ſame paſſage which they have out of the 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chapter of Saint <hi>Mathew, that the finne againſt the Holy-Ghoſt ſhall not be forgiven neither in this world, nor in the world to come.</hi> But I anſwer that <hi>this world to come</hi> cannot be Purgatory, for they ſay that Purgatory is now already, but by this world to come, is truly meant the day of judgement; and our Saviours mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38564:15"/>is, that he that ſinneth againſt the Holy-Ghoſt, ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed both in this life, and alſo after this life eternally in hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe to that in the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Chapter of the 1. Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> where it is ſpoken <hi>of gold, wood, precious ſtones, hay, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer, that it is alſo an Allegoricall ſpeech, and that it is not meant of the torment of the ſoule after death.</p>
               <p>So then we ſee plainly that this their Purgatory is but imaginary, and and cannot be proved out of the word of God, wherein there is not ſo much as any mention made thereof; only forged by them, to maintaine and uphold the Popes dignity, who by this invention finds quicke ſale for his pardons and Indulgences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of merits and juſtification by Works.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Church of Rome teacheth, that a man by his good works may merit eternall ſalvation; and that a man is juſtified before God by the workes of the Law, and thereupon to make the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion ſeeme the more odious, they lay to our charge that we teach, that good workes are altogether unprofitable, and no way conducing to ſalvation; and that it is faith alone that juſtifieth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any need at all of performing any other duties of Chriſtianity. An abhominable doctrine it is indeed, and worthy of moſt ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as aboliſhing all honeſty and vertue, and ſetting looſe the reines to all manner of wickedneſſe and impiety.</p>
               <p>To the contrary we of the Proteſtant Religion purged from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, hold that good works are abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, and that there is no other way to obtaine everlaſting life; that <hi>faith without works is dead,</hi> and cannot juſtifie; that good works ſerve to glorifie God, to edifie our brethren, and to bring us to eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; onely we deny that good workes can merit ſalvation, they are the way indeed whereby we come to everlaſting happineſſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38564:15"/>but not the price whereby we purchaſe it; which is already ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently purchaſed, by the free redemption of our Lord Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               <p>We ſay moreover, that although faith alone, and without good works cannot juſtifie, yet faith hath the propriety to juſtifie us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; as the eyes cannot ſee without the help of the eares, and yet the eyes alone have the gift of ſeeing.</p>
               <p>Now that we cannot merit any thing at Gods hands, I ſhall plainly prove by theſe five reaſons following:</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it is our duty to doe any good worke; whatſoever we doe, as our Saviour himſelfe telleth us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. <hi>When ye ſhall have done all thoſe things which are commanded, ſay, we are unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervants, we have done all that which was our duty to doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>the good which we doe comes from God;</hi> and conſequently cannot merit any thing for us at Gods hands; for we doe but give him that which is his owne already.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, our good works profit him nothing; he hath no need of our ſervice, although we have great need of his grace.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, our good works at the beſt are but imperfect, and have alwayes ſome infirmity in the performance of them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly and laſtly, there is no proportion at all betwixt our good works and the kingdome of heaven: To gaine ſuch an excellent purchaſe, there needs a price inſinitely excellent, ſuch as the merits of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the holy Scripture ſaith, that <hi>eternall life is the gift of God,</hi> and not to be purchaſed by mans merits; as the Apoſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in the 6<hi rend="sup">h</hi> Chapter <hi>of Rom. The wages of ſin</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is death, but the gift of God is eternall life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> and <hi>Epheſians</hi> the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapter, <hi>by grace we are ſaved, through faith, and that not of your ſelves. It is the gift of God, not of workes, leſt any man ſhould boast.</hi> Wherefore God calleth us his children, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent heires, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. to the end that we may know that we can lay no right to the kingdome of God as a purchaſe, which we have merited by good works; but as children, and in Jeſus Chriſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heires hereunto. Surely, then thoſe that goe about to purchaſe eternall ſalvation in a mercinary way by their owne merits, renounce the title of being Gods children, and conſequently loſe their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. Some there be, who to ſweeten this their hodge-podge, ſay that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38564:16"/>we merit by the grace of God, who gives us grace to merit; a tenet altogether as falſe as hypocriticall and abſurd; for the chiefe and principall cauſe why our good workes are not meritorious, is becauſe they proceed from the grace of God. I pray what doth that man merit of me that gives me that which is mine owne alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?</p>
               <p>I confeſſe indeed that the holy Scripture ſaith, <hi>that God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our good workes, and that our reward is great in heauen; and that even for a cup of cold water we ſhall not loſe our reward;</hi> but this reward is no way merited by us; as a father gives his childe ſome reward, it may be for writing a line or two out of a Copy, or ſuch like, which he doth not becauſe the worke deſerves it, but becauſe it is his childe.</p>
               <p>So God accepteth of us freely in Chriſt Jeſus, not for our works ſake, but rewards our works, though never ſo imperfect and unworthy, only becauſe we are his children.</p>
               <p>It is no marvell then if thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> profeſſe that they doubt of their ſalvation; for it is impoſſible to build a ſtedfaſt aſſurance thereof on ſo weake a foundation as our owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; whereas indeed we ought to ground it onely on the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veable foundation of Gods promiſe in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Let us conclude then with the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 3 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Romanes, that a man is juſtified by faith without the deeds of the Law, and that we are iuſtified freely by his grace through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I doe not ſay but that before men we are juſtified by workes, that is to ſay, knowne to be juſt; for men cannot judge of our faith, becauſe they cannot diſcerne it. And thus Saint <hi>James</hi> chap. 2. teacheth <hi>that Abraham was juſtified by works,</hi> but he was not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by that meanes before God: As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes: If Abraham</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were juſtified by workes, he hath whereof to glory, but not before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heare likewiſe what the ſame Apoſtle ſaith in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapter to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> verſe the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>We have beleeved in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be iuſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law, for by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified.</hi> And in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Tim. Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>God hath ſaved us, and called us with an holy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38564:16"/>calling, not according to our workes, but according to his owne pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and grace which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus, before the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X. <hi>Of Works of Super-erogation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WOrkes of Super-erogation may fitly be termed the Popes grand Maſter-peece to ſupport his dignity.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle Saint <hi>James</hi> Chapter the 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith, <hi>that in many things we offend all.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 1. booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> Chapter the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſaith, that <hi>there is no man that ſinneth not.</hi> And in the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> he ſaith, <hi>that a iuſt man falleth ſeven times,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>many times.</hi> The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he doth the evill that he would not doe, and that ſinne dwelleth in him.</hi> Wherefore our Saviour taught his Diſciples to ſay every day, <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It appeares then plainly, that the moſt juſt amongſt men faile in many things, and doe not perfectly fulfill the Law of God.</p>
               <p>To the contrary the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth, that a man may not only perfectly fulfill the Law of God; but alſo that many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe more good works then God hath commanded, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are more righteous then God would have them.</p>
               <p>Theſe good works, more perfect forſooth, and more excellent then thoſe which God hath commanded, they call works of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation, the which a man is not bound to performe, neither is he to be puniſhed if he doth them not; but if he doth them, and obſerves them, he doth thereby purchaſe unto himſelfe a degree of glory in Paradiſe above the ordinary ranke of Saints, who having done no more but what God hath commanded, have alſo for their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour nothing but eternall life.</p>
               <p>This doctrine is altogether as ſenſleſſe as devilliſh, and againſt all reaſon: For God hath commanded us in his Law, <hi>that we love,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38564:17"/>that we ſerve him and obey him with all our heart, with all our ſtrength:</hi> If any man doth then more then God hath commanded in his Lawes, he ſerves God, and loves him more then with all his ſtrength, which is as much to ſay, as that he doth that which he is not able to doe.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the Apoſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chapter the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to give our ſelves to all things that are juſt and honeſt, and to all vertue whatſoever. If then theſe works of Super-erogation be either juſt or honeſt, they are alſo commanded.</p>
               <p>And if thoſe who give themſelves to theſe works of Super-erogation have power to performe them, is it not God who hath given them that power? And if God doth give them that power, is it not that they ſhould ſerve him? They are therefore bound to doe thoſe works; and if ſo, then are they no more works of Super-erogation.</p>
               <p>But if we conſider this ſeriouſly, we ſhall find that theſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who boaſt that they doe more then God doth either require or command, doe abſolutely conceit themſelves to be farre more juſt and more holy then the Angels themſelves: For all the perfection of the Angels conſiſteth in doing Gods will, and not in doing more then he commands them; as it is ſaid <hi>Pſalme</hi> 103. <hi>Angels that excell in ſtrength doe his Commandements, hearkening unto the voice of his word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, I ſay more, that all the juſtice of our Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, as man, conſiſted in nothing elſe then <hi>in doing the will of his Father in heaven,</hi> as you may reade in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>I came downe from heaven</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>not to doe mine owne will, but the will of him that ſent me.</hi> And in the 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chapter to the <hi>Hebrewes, Loe, I come to doe thy will ô God.</hi> So then theſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with their works of Super-erogation, will be found by this reckoning more juſt and more perfect then Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it muſt needs be, that in doing theſe works of Super-erogation, they doe either the will of God, or elſe their owne: The will of God they doe not; for they are workes which God hath not commanded, they doe therefore their owne. It ſeemes then by this that they conceive their owne will, to be more perfect and more excellent then the will of God.</p>
               <p>And how comes it to paſſe that perpetuall virginity, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38564:17"/>and monaſteriall vowes (which with many other ſuch like they terme works of Super-erogation) ſhould be better then the Commandement of God, which commands us <hi>to love him with all our heart,</hi> &amp;c. Howbeit to love God is alwayes a good, holy, and neceſſary duty; but a ſingle life, and martyrdome, and ſuch like are things in themſelves moſt ſinfull and wicked, if they be not done in love to God. The love of God is alwayes holy and good, but theſe things may be done in hypocriſie, or through deſpaire and ambition, and are no way good if they be not done for the love of God.</p>
               <p>Martyrdome is a good and holy duty when God cals us thereunto; but to incurre it without neceſſity can be termed nothing elſe but prepoſterous timerity: But when we are called thereunto by God, in ſuch kind, as that to eſcape it we muſt deny the faith of Chriſt, then it is abſolutely a thing moſt neceſſary, and expreſly commanded in Gods Word.</p>
               <p>To give all ones goods to the poore were a knaviſh part in a man that hath many children, &amp;c. The monaſticall oath of never mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying is an occaſion and cauſe of all manner of idleneſſe and filthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence.</p>
               <p>Finally, God commands us to doe <hi>whatſoever things are iust, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are good, whatſoever things are pure:</hi> If then theſe men will doe more then God commands them, they muſt of neceſſity doe that which he abſolutely forbids, and ſo heap unto themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI. <hi>Of the Superaboundant Satisfactions of Saints and Monkes, which the Pope diſtributes by Indulgences.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holdeth that there be diverſe Saints who have not much ſinned, and yet have ſuffered very much; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38564:18"/>conſequently that they have ſuffered more puniſhments then their ſinnes deſerved. The overplus is that which they call ſuperaboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſatisfactions; that is to ſay, the overplus of that which theſe Saints have payed unto God more then they owed him; of this ranke of Saints are chiefly the Monkes, for they ſay that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſo many good works, and undergoe ſo many puniſhments for ſatisfactions, that they have enough left to help other men.</p>
               <p>This overplus leſt it ſhould be loſt, the Pope gathers into the treaſury of the Church, and diſtributes it to the people by Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and converts it into ſatisfactions for other mens offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>It is then a very ſaucy preſuppoſition that God will accept of the laſhes with a whip, of the beatings, of the faſts and pilgrimages of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> or Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> in full ſatisfaction for another mans ſinnes: As if a Iudge would deale any thing the kinder with a priſoner becauſe a friend of his whipt himſelfe, or faſted more then he was commanded.</p>
               <p>It is alſo to accuſe God Almighty of injuſtice, to thinke that he inflicts more puniſhments on any man then his ſinnes doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <p>It is not to know the greatneſſe of ſinne, and to be ignorant of the puniſhment due thereunto, to conceive that a few faſts and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, or any miſeries that are to be endured in this life, can be a ſatisfaction more then ſufficient for the ſame: For our Saviour in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he that calleth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foole ſhall be in danger of hell-fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if the ſatisfaction of Ieſus Chriſt be ſufficient for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to all our ſinnes, what need we the ſatisfactions of Saints? Why ſhould we thinke that God will take two payments for one and the ſame debt, when the firſt is ſufficient?</p>
               <p>Moreover, God rewards us to the full here on earth for all our good works and endeavours, how is it then that we ſhould merit any thing to another thereby? A fooliſh conceit it is indeed, as if the ſame money which I imploy to buy me a houſe, ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſerve over and above for the payment of another mans debts. And in a thing ſo holy and important, as touching our reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with God in Chriſt, is it lawfull to forge articles of faith without any ground for the truth thereof out of the word of God?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38564:18"/>For where is the leaſt proofe for this in all the holy Scripture? who ſeeth not that it was invented on purpoſe to increaſe the Popes treaſury, and to exalt his Empire? who hereby with his pardons and Indulgences amaſſeth unto himſelfe infinite riches.</p>
               <p>I would very willingly learne who it was that firſt put the Saints ſatisfactions into the treaſury of the Church? when began this diſtribution? how ſhall we know certainly whether God doth receive theſe ſatisfactions as ſufficient? why had not the Prieſts in the old Teſtament ſuch a treaſury wherein to keep the ſuperaboundant ſatisfactions of <hi>Noah, Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. which overplus it ſeems they have loſt by ill husbandry. What is the cauſe why our Saviour Chriſt Ieſus, nor his Apoſtles were not adviſed to ſpeake of this Treaſury? or of one mans ſatisfying for another? Surely Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was aſleep when he ſaid, <hi>that every man ſhall beare his owne burthen, Gal.</hi> 6. or elſe they will make themſelves wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> But whether it be allowable by Gods Word or no, ſo it be any way conducing to the Popes profit it matters not with them, ſo the Pope hath a fee it's no matter whether God hath any honour. Thus doe they both diſhonour God and wrong their owne ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of the preſence of the Lords body in the Sacrament, and of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF there were none other abuſe in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſave only this one errour of Tranſubſtantiation, it were of it ſelfe ſufficient to drive away from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> any man that is carefull for the ſalvation of his ſoule. The holy Scripture declareth that no Idolaters ſhall enter into the kingdome of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. and ſurely there can be no greater Idolatry then to call a morſell of bread his god, and his Creator, and to adore a god made with a few words; a god that may be ſtollen away, a god that may be mouldy, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38564:19"/>up with wormes, and thoſe termes which they uſe, of eating God, of lifting up God, of carrying God about in proceſſion, me thinkes ſhould make a true Chriſtians haire to ſtand on end, to heare ſuch intollerable blaſphemies, whereby God Almighty is ſo greatly diſhonoured, and the Chriſtian Religion ſo expoſed to the reproach of Pagans and Infidels.</p>
               <p>The Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtrive to prove this their Tranſubſtantiation from that paſſage of our Saviour, which they alleadge cropt and maimed, not mentioning either the foregoing, or the following words, where we find that <hi>Jeſus tooke bread, brake it, bleſſed, and gave it to them, ſaying, take, eat, this is my body, which is broken for you, doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> It appeares then that our Saviour g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve bread, and it is manifeſt that he gave it not till after the conſecration; it was therefore bread after the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Our Saviour ſaith, that <hi>the bread is his body,</hi> not that the bread is changed or tranſubſtantiated into his body; ſo that the bread is not the body of Chriſt <hi>Capernaitically</hi> or groſſely, but ſacramentally and ſpiritually.</p>
               <p>Moreover, our Saviour in the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſaith, <hi>me ye have not alwayes,</hi> which were falſe if he were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes incloſed in a wafer cake. To this they anſwer, that we have him no more viſibly. I reply, that to have Jeſus Chriſt inviſibly, is nevertheleſſe to have him; that man ſhould lye that ſhould ſay he hath no money, becauſe it is in his coffer. So likewiſe in the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpell, ver. 17. <hi>I goe to the Father</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) which alſo were an untruth if he did ſtill remaine in a peece of bread.</p>
               <p>All this they pretend under the ſhadow of theſe words, <hi>this is my body,</hi> for the meaning whereof they will not receive Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> expoſition, who thus delivereth it unto us, <hi>the bread which we breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p>And I pray how many times in the Scripture is it ſaid that we are the body of Chriſt? doth it therefore follow that we be tranſubſtantiated into his body?</p>
               <p>We ſee then into how many blaſphemies, how many groſſe abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and contradictions they run into to defend this their fantaſticall Tranſubſtantion; having no proofe at all for it out of Gods word; what they have out of their unwritten word I know not, neither doe I care.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38564:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A word or two now of the Idolatrous ſacrifice of the Maſſe. Hereupon it was that I firſt found the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at a fault: For I often called on them to ſhew me ſome paſſage out of the word of God, that commandeth the ſacrifice of the body of Chriſt Jeſus, but they could none of them ever ſhew me any: Some forſooth will take the inſtitution thereof from thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>doe this,</hi> which they interpret, <hi>ſacrifice my body;</hi> but this interpretation is of their owne invention. Others alleadge that paſſage of our Saviour, <hi>this is my body,</hi> for the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of it: But what if it were ſuch a body indeed as they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it (which notwithſtanding is very falſe) can they conclude, becauſe our Saviour ſaid, <hi>this is my body,</hi> that he commanded the ſacrifice of his body? Briefly, they cannot alleadge any paſſage out of the word of God, which might prove the inſtitution of this their moſt idolatrous ſacrifice. And indeed, ſeeing the ſacrifice of the death of Ieſus Chriſt is ſufficient, what need is there to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice him any more? Againe, through the whole paſſage of the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Lords Supper, there is not the leaſt ſigne or mention of any ſacrifice, neither did the Apoſtles any worſhip at all, which is a thing moſt neceſſary in every ſacrifice, and more eſpecially in a ſacrifice newly inſtituted, for a preſident and example for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> ſaith, <hi>that we are ſanctified through the offering of the body of Ieſus Chriſt once for all.</hi> We ſee then plainly, that the death of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Ieſus is the onely ſacrifice, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe offered up unto God for all our ſinnes; ſo that it is meere fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery in us to preſume to ſacrifice that body againe in ſuch a tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comædiall manner as that of the Maſſe, which hath already been received as a ſufficient ſacrifice for all our ſins.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in every ſacrifice, that which they ſacrifice ought to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38564:20"/>conſecrated; that which they pretend to ſacrifice, is the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which cannot be conſecrated; for who can conſecrate the Sonne of God? ſo likewiſe the thing conſecrated which they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in the Maſſe, cannot be the bread, for they ſay that it is no more bread after the conſecration; and although they ſhould ſay that it were bread after the conſecration, yet ſo it is that neither bread nor any other creature can be thought a reaſonable ſacrifice for our redemption.</p>
               <p>Certainly this was invented onely for the maintenance of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of lazie lubbers, which they call Prieſts; for take away the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and they have no imployment, and truly by this meanes I thinke they get as much as might competently main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, were it not for the Popes bawdy houſes, which conſume moſt part of their revenues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of the taking away the cup in the Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are yet many errours in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the moſt abuſive and injurious errour in my opinion is the taking away of the cup in the Sacrament from the Laity, contrary to our Saviours inſtitution, and to the practiſe of the Apoſtles, who gave the people the holy Communion under both ſignes.</p>
               <p>The firſt inſtitution of the Sacrament was when our Saviour <hi>tooke the cup and bleſſed it, and gave it to his Diſciples, ſaying, drinke ye all of this.</hi> Now if in theſe words, <hi>drinke ye all of this,</hi> our Saviour ſpeaks to none but the Paſtors or Miniſters of the Church, it muſt conſequently follow, that the commandement to eat, which is in the aforegoing words appertaine alſo to the Paſtors onely; and then there is no commandement at all whereby the Laity is commanded to receive the bread.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38564:20"/>
               <p>And it is cleare that the Apoſtles receiving the Sacrament of our Saviour, received it not then as Paſtors, but as Sheep and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; And though they had received it as Paſtors and Miniſters of the Church, did not our Saviour thanke you, when he ſaid unto them, <hi>doe this as oft as ye doe it in remembrance of me,</hi> intimate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that they ought to adminiſter it unto the people in the ſame manner as he did adminiſter it unto them.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> underſtandeth it ſo, as you may ſee by that commandement which he gives the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in his 1. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Chap. 11. <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drinke of that cup.</hi> It is manifeſt that this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both <hi>to eat of that bread, and drinke of that cup</hi> is made unto thoſe that ought to examine themſelves; but every one ought to examine himſelfe before he come to receive that holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; therefore every one ought to receive both <hi>that bread and that cup</hi> whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>And in the beginning of that ſame 1. Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> it appeareth that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did write to all the people of <hi>Corinth,</hi> excepting none that did call upon the name of the Lord Jeſus. Theſe are the words: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſurely it is ſomewhat conſiderable, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeemeth by this meanes to labour to deprive the people of eternall life: For the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conceive thoſe words of our Saviour in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpell, <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloud, ye have no life in you,</hi> to be ſpoken of the Sacrament of the Euchariſt: And if it be ſo, it is manifeſt, that in taking away the cup from the Laity, they deprive them of eternall life.</p>
               <p>Their excuſe for this is, that the bread is in the body, ſo that in eating the body, they drinke the bloud alſo. To the which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that to receive the bloud ſo in the Sacrament is not to drinke it; but our Saviour ſaith expreſly, <hi>Except ye drinke,</hi> &amp;c. And if in eating the body they drinke alſo the bloud, the Prieſt doth by this reckoning drinke twiſe, once when he ſwallowes downe the body, and againe when he drinks off the cup.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:38564:21"/>
               <p>They produce likewiſe certaine paſſages of the Scripture, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is ſpoken of the breaking of the bread, without mentioning the cup? I anſwer, that in thoſe paſſages, as it is not ſaid that the people ſhould receive the cup; ſo neither is it ſaid that the Prieſts ſhould receive it: If then by theſe paſſages, they will gather that the people are not obliged to take the cup, I may alſo from thence gather that the Prieſts are not obliged; for there is no more ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the one then of the other. Beſides, we reade in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 9. <hi>that Mephiboſheth did eat bread at Davids table;</hi> may we conclude from thence that he never dranke, becauſe it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed?</p>
               <p>The manner of the celebration of the Lords Supper ought to be taken from our Saviours firſt expreſſed inſtitutions, and formall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
               <p>The originall ſpring of this groſſe abuſe proceedeth from pride and ambition, for by this meanes thoſe of the Clergy raiſe their dignity farre above the people, whom they exclude from one halfe of the Sacrament; and doe hereby make themſelves in this reſpect equall unto Kings, who together with them receive the Sacrament under both ſignes. And the Pope hath a prerogative above all men elſe, in that he doth ſucke the wine out of the Calice with a quill.</p>
               <p>Thus have we briefly diſcovered the manifold and great abuſes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and how ſtrangely they delude the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with their imaginary and idolatrous ſervices; how abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods holy word are all their tenets; and how through the whole profeſſion of their Religion they ſeeke infinitely Gods diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and are wholly bent for the advancement of the Popes dignity. I beſeech Almighty God to give us his bleſſed Spirit to diſcern betwixt good and evill, and ſo to relye upon the merits of our Saviour Chriſt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus, by a lively faith, that at length we may obtaine that immortall crowne of glory, prepared f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all faithfull perſons in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, to whom with the Father Almighty, and the glorious Spirit, be aſcribed and given all poſſible praiſe, thanksgiving and obedience, for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:38564:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
